Xavier University Higher Learning Commission accreditation records
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections
Xavier University Higher Learning Commission accreditation records
1914-2012
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections Phone: 513-745-4821 http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)
6 linear feet (12 boxes)
This is a collection of records related to the accreditation of Xavier University from the Higher Learning Commission, previously known as the North Central Association of Colleges and Schools.
XUA-43
History of Xavier University and Higher Learning Commission accreditation
Since Xavier University was initially accredited in 1925 by the North Central Association of Colleges and Schools (now known as the Higher Learning Commission), the university has been regularly reviewed for re-accreditation.
Xavier University is accredited by the Higher Learning Commission of the North Central Association of Colleges and Schools (HLC). Xavier first joined the North Central Association of College and Schools, as the HLC was originally called, in 1925. There have been regular comprehensive reviews of the Xavier since that time along with focused visits by a review team. These occurred approximately every ten years. Accreditation was lost in 1934 for about one year over athletic issues pertaining principally to the football program, but it has been held continuously since 1935. Until the late 1990s, the Higher Learning Commission of the North Central Association of Colleges and School was simply referred to as the North Central Association of Colleges and Schools (NCA). In earlier years, the official "visit" of the NCA review team, which took place every ten years, was sometimes referred to as the "Survey." Similarly, the institutional Self-Study which Xavier now undergoes in preparation for the Visit was referred to as the "Schedules."
Scope and Content
This collection includes correspondence, institutional self-studies, reports and other materials dealing with the accreditation of Xavier University by the Higher Learning Commission, previously known as the North Central Association of Colleges and Schools.
Statement of Arrangement
The materials in the collection are arranged chronologically.
Separated Material
Electronic files dealing with Higher Learning Commission (North Central Association) accreditation can also be found on the Xavier University Archives storage drive. Please consult the archives staff.
Restrictions on Access
Restricted access. Please contact the Xavier University archives staff.
Accruals
Additional documents may be added to this collection.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects:
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Accreditation; Universities and colleges--Accreditation--Ohio
Organizations/Corporations:
Higher Learning Commission
Detailed Description of The Collection
- HLC / NCA Correspondence, 1914-1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Correspondence from December 23, 1914 to March 8, 1934
- HLC / NCA Correspondence, 1934 March-April (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Correspondence, final reports and other materials pertaining to the two official visits (surveys) of Xavier by NCA review teams which took place on March 8 and 9, 1934 and on April 18, 1934.
- HLC / NCA Correspondence, 1934 April-October (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Correspondence from April 20, 1934 to October 27, 1934.
- NCA Manual, 1934 April 19 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  In this folder: 1. North Central Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools: Commission on Institutions of Higher Education: Manual, April 19, 1934.
- Xavier Schedules for Visit of February 25-26, 1935, 1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  In this folder: The Schedules which consist of information, statistics and other data supplied by Xavier to the review team prior to the Visit or Survey which took place on February 25-26, 1935.
- Papers Pertaining to the Visit of February 25-26, 1935, 1934-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  In this folder: Documents pertaining to the official visit (survey) to Xavier of the NCA review team, including the final report, which took place on February 25-26, 1935.
- Correspondence, 1940-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  In this folder: Correspondence from January, 1940 to December, 1946.
- Xavier Schedules for Visit of February 5-6, 1947, 1946, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  In this folder: "The Schedules" which Xavier completed and submitted to NCA prior to the 1947 visitation (survey) and review.
- Papers Pertaining to Visit of February 5-6, 1947, 1947, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  In this folder: Materials pertaining to the official visit (survey) of Xavier by the NCA review team which took place on February 5-6, 1947, including the team's final report and a response by Xavier's president.
- Correspondence, 1948-1957 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  In this folder: Correspondence from April 9, 1948 to May 24, 1957.
- Xavier Schedules for Visit of May 1-2, 1958, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  In this folder: Materials pertaining to the official visit (survey) of Xavier by the NCA review team which took place on May 1-2, 1958, including the Schedules and other documents and correspondence.
- Papers Pertaining to Visit of May 1-2, 1958, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  In this folder: In early March, 1957, President Paul L. O'Connor,S.J., acting on the recommendation of the Academic Council, appointed a committee "to recommend how we can best study the purposes of our instructional program. eventually we want a full statement of our objectives that will serve to guide curricular decisions and stimulate improvement of instruction." The work of this committee began in March 1957 and ended somewhere around mid-January, 1959. This folder contains, in chronological order, papers, documents, reports and surveys pertaining to the work of the committee. While this study was apparently done independently of the NCA visit, it clearly played a prominent role in Xavier's preparation for the visit. All of these papers were found among the materials pertaining to the NCA preparations of 1958.
- Papers Pertaining to Visit of May 1-2, 1958, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  In this folder: 1. Final report of the review team after the visit (survey) which took place on May 1-2, 1958; 2. Correspondence from May 20, 1958 to October 23, 1959; 3. A report of unknown purpose which was found among these papers.
- Correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  In this folder: Correspondence from January 18, 1960 to September 27, 1961.
- Correspondence, 1962-1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  In this folder: Correspondence from March 2, 1962 to September 25, 1966.
- Papers Preparing For Visit of March 4-6, 1968, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  In this folder: Documents and papers preparing for the Visit of March 4-6, 1968, dated from October 13, 1966 to April 3, 1967.
- Papers Preparing for Visit of March 4-6, 1968, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  In this folder: Documents and papers preparing for the Visit of March 4-6, 1968, dated from April 4, 1967 to September 14, 1967.
- Papers Preparing for Visit of March 4-6, 1968, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  In this folder: Documents and papers preparing for the Visit of March 4-6, 1968, dated from October 3, 1967 to February 28, 1968.
- Profiles and Institutional Data for Visit of March 4-6, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  In this folder: "Xavier University Profiles: North Central Review, 1968: and "Xavier University Basic Institutional Data: North Central Review, 1968."
- Profiles and Institutional Data for Visit of March 4-6, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  In this folder: Second copies of "Xavier University Profiles: North Central Review, 1968" and "Xavier University Basic Institutional Data: North Central Review, 1968."
- Official Report on Visit of March 4-6, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  In this folder: "Report of a Visit to Xavier University, March4-6, 1968, for the Commission on Colleges and Universities of the North Central Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools." (three copies)
- Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  In this folder: Correspondence from March 12, 1968 to April 24, 1970.
- Papers Preparing for Visit of March 13-15, 1978, 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  In this folder: Documents and correspondence pertaining to Xavier's preparations for the visit.
- North Central Association Visitation, March 13-15, 1978, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Two volume self study of Xavier University: Volume I: Self Study; Volume II: Basic Institutional Data
- North Central Association Visitation of Xavier, March 13-15, 1978, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Xavier University Self Study, 1977: Volume one: Self Study. This copy of the Self Study is complete and readable, but it contains some handwritten notes and comments. the second volume of the Basic Institutional Data is missing.
- North Central Association Visitation of Xavier, March 13-15, 1978, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Xavier University Self Study, 1977: Volume One: Self Study; Volume Two: Basic Institutional Data
- Official Report of the Visit on March 13-15, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Includes "A Report of a Visit to Xavier University for the Commission on Institutions of Higher Education of the North Central Association of Colleges and Schools;" a rough draft of "A Report of a Visit to Xavier University for the Commission of Institutions of Higher Education of the North Central Association of Colleges and Schools;' and a "Guide for the Evaluation of Institutions of Higher Learning."
- North Central Association Visitation of Xavier, March 6-8, 1989, 1986-1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  In this folder: 1. Correspondence and other preparatory materials for the 1989 visitation; 2. Memos, documents, statistics and other papers produced and gathered by several subcommittees involved in preparing Xavier's Self Study, especially the subcommittee on the Faculty and Instructional Staff.
- North Central Association Visitation of Xavier, March 6-8, 1989, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  In this folder: 1. A Student Opinion Survey administered by the Xavier University North Central Steering Committee. The results of the survey are missing.; 2. A Questionnaire for the Faculty administered by the Steering Committee and a computer printout with the results.
- North Central Association Visitation of Xavier, March 6-8, 1989, 1989 March (Box 5, Folder 5)
  In this folder: "Report of a Visit to Xavier University for the Commission on Institutions of Higher Education of the North Central Association of Colleges and Schools." (Three copies)
- North Central Association Visitation of Xavier, March 6-8, 1989, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  In this folder: 1. Xavier University Self Study, 1988; 2. Xavier University Self Study Supplement, 1988.
- North Central Association Visitation of Xavier, March 6-8, 1989, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  In this folder: 1. Xavier University Self Study, 1988 (copy two); 2. Xavier University Self Study Supplement, 1988 (copy two).
- North Central Association Visitation of Xavier, March 6-8, 1989, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  In this folder: 1. Xavier University Self Study, 1988 (copy three); 2. Xavier University Self Study Supplement, 1988 (copy three).
- North Central Association Visitation of Xavier, March 6-8, 1989, 1988, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  In this folder: Xavier University Self Study, 1988, Preliminary Draft (Copy One)
- North Central Association Visitation of Xavier, March 6-8, 1989, 1987, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  In this folder: Xavier University Self Study, 1988, Preliminary draft (Copy Two)
- Proposal for Off-Campus MBA Programs, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  In this folder: Xavier's proposal for conducting on-site (off-campus) Masters of Business Administration programs at General Electric Aircraft Engines in Evendale, Ohio, and at Midway College in Midway, Kentucky. The proposal is dated January 11, 1996.
- North Central Visitation of Xavier, April 19-21, 1999, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  In this folder: 1. The Xavier Steering Committee: Minutes and other papers pertaining to the activities of the committee that prepared the Self Study for the NCA visitation in 1999; 2. The Xavier Self Study Resources Subcommittee: Minutes and other papers pertaining to the activities of the subcommittee that studied Xavier's resources in preparation for the 1999 Self Study.
- North Central Association Visitation of Xavier, April 19-21, 1999, 1994, 1998, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  In this folder: Documents, reports, statistics and other materials produced or gathered by the Steering Committee in preparation for the Self Study of 1999. The following topics are included: Accounting Practices, Budget, Endowment, External Support (Cornerstone Capital Gifts Campaign); Facilities; Faculty and Faculty Survey; Investment Plan; Human Resources).
- North Central Association Visitation of Xavier, April 19-21, 1999, 1991, 1998, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  In this folder: In a continuation of the previous folder, this folder includes documents, reports, statistics and other materials produced or gathered by the Steering Committee in preparation for the Self Study of 1999. The following topics are included: Survey of Departmental Chairs; Library and Instructional Media; Classroom Survey; Tuition Plan; Mission and Jesuit Identity; Safety and Campus Police; University Student Center and Student Development; Preliminary Draft of the Self Study; Technology and Information Systems.
- North Central Association Visitation of Xavier, April 19-21, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  In this folder: Xavier University Self Study, 1999 (Copy One). this copy appears to be complete. It has 13 appendices including the Basic Institutional Data.
- North Central Association Visitation of Xavier, April 19-21, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  In this folder: Xavier University Self Study, 1999 (Copy Two). This copy appears to be complete. It has 13 appendices including the Basic Institutional Data.
- North Central Association Visitation of Xavier, April 19-21, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  In this folder: Xavier University Self Study, 1999 (Copy Three). This copy appears to be complete. It has 13 appendices including the Basic Institutional Data.
- North Central Association Visitation of Xavier, April 19-21, 1999, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  In this folder: "Handbook of Accreditation" (Second Edition, September, 1997)
- North Central Association Visitation of Xavier, April 19-21, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  In this folder: Report of a Comprehensive Evaluation of Xavier University for the Commission on Institutions of Higher Education of the North Central Association of Colleges and Universities. Final report of visiting committee (Two copies)
- North Central Association Visitation of Xavier, April 19-21, 1999, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  In this folder: 1. Xavier's Supplementary Report on Assessment dated April, 2001, mandated by the 1999 visiting team (2 copies); 2. HLC's response to the Supplementary Report dated July 26, 2001.
- Higher Learning Commission / North Central Association Visit of March 30-April 1, 2009, 2007 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  In this folder: Documents from the 2007 annual meeting of the Higher Learning Commission concerning the preparation of an institutional Self Study.
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 3- April 1, 2009 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  In this folder: Xavier University Institutional Snapshot, March 5, 2009.
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30-April 1, 2009 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  In this folder: The logistical preparations for the on-site visit of the HLC team including details of the daily schedule of events.
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30-April 1, 2009, 2006-2009 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  In this folder: 1. Some archival notes on the history of this visit; 2. Two copies of the final Report of a Comprehensive Evaluation Visit to Xavier University, both the Assurance Section and the Advancement Section; 3. Correspondence between Xavier University and the offices of the Higher Learning Commission prior to and after the visit.
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30-April 1, 2009 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  In this folder: Xavier University HLC Self-Study, 2009 (Copy One).
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30- April 1, 2009 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  In this folder: Xavier University HLC Self-Study, 2009 (Copy Two).
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30-April 1, 2009, 2002-2009 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  In this folder: Printed copies of the supporting evidence for the Introduction to the 2009 HLC Self-Study, pages 3 to 25.
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30-April 1, 2009, 2001-2009 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  In this folder: Printed copies of the supporting evidence for Criterion One, "Mission and Integrity" of the 2009 HLC Self-Study, pages 29 to 60.
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30- April 1, 2009, 2008-2009 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  In this folder: Printed copies of the supporting evidence for Criterion Two, "Preparing for the Future," of the 2009 HLC Self-Study, pages 63 to 86.
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30- April 1, 2009, 2008-2009 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  In this folder: Printed copies of the supporting evidence for Criterion Three, "Student Learning and effective Teaching," of the 2009 HLC Self-Study, pages 89 to 117.
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30-April 1, 2009, 2004-2009, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  In this folder: Printed copies of the supporting evidence for Criterion Four, "Acquisition, Discovery and Application of Knowledge," of the 2009 HLC Self-Study, pages 121 to 144
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30- April 1, 2009, 2008-2009 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  In this folder: Printed copies of the supporting evidence for Criterion Five, "Engagement and Service,"of the 2009 HLC Self-Study, pages 147 to 175.
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30 to April 1, 2009, 2008-2009 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  In this folder: 1 Miscellaneous supporting evidence in preparation for the visit of the HLC team; 2. CD of information about the visit of the HLC team (copied onto the Archives Permanent Storage Drive).
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit March 30-April 1, 2009, 2003-2009, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  In this folder: These materials came from the Office of the Associate Provost for Academic Affairs, Dr. Kandi Stinson. They are a collection of documents and reports which her office gathered as reference matreials for the preparation and writing of the HLC Self-Study. The paper in this folder pertain to the First Criterion, Items "A" and "B."
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30-April 1, 2009, 2004-2009, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  In this folder: These materials came from the Office of the Associate Provost for Academic Affairs, Dr. Kandi Stinson. They are a collection of documents and reports which her office gathered as reference materials for the preparation and writing of the HLC Self-Study. The papers in this folder pertain to the First Criterion, Item "C."
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30 to April 1, 2009, 2003-2009 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  In this folder: These materials came from the Office of the Associate Provost for Academic Affiars, Dr. Kandi Stinson. they are a collection of documents and reports which her office gathered as reference materials for the preparation and writing of the HLC Self-Study. the papers in this folder pertain to the First Criterion, Items "D" and "E."
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30 to April 1, 2009, 2008-2009 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  In this folder: These materials came from the Office of the Associate Provost for Academic Affairs, Dr. Kandi Stinson. They are a collection of documents and reports which her office gathered as reference materials for the preparation and writing of the HLC Self-Study. The papers in this folder pertain to Criterion Two, Item "A."
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30-April 1, 2009, 2003-2009, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  In this folder: These materials came from the Office of the Associate Provost for Academic Affairs, Dr. Kandi Stinson. They are a collection of documents and reports which her office gathered as reference materials for the preparation and writing of the HLC Self-Study. the papers in this folder pertain to Criterion Two, Items "B" and "C."
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30-April 1, 2009, 2002-2008 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  In this folder: These materials came from the Office of the Associate Provost for Academic Affairs, Dr. Kandi Stinson. They are a collection of documents and reports which her office gathered as reference materials for the preparation and writing of the HLC Self-Study. The paper in this folder pertain to Criterion Two, Item "D."
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30-April 1, 2009, 2002-2009 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  These materials came from the Office of the Associate Provost for Academic Affairs, Dr. Kandi Stinson. They are a collection of documents and reports which her office gathered as reference materials for the preparation and writing of the HLC Self-Study. The papers in this folder pertain to Criterion Three, Items "A" and "B."
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30-April 1, 2009, 2001-2009; undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  These materials came from the Office of the Associate Provost for Academic Affairs, Dr. Kandi Stinson. They are a collection of documents and reports which her office gathered as reference materials for the preparation and writing of the HLC Self-Study. the papers in this folder pertain to Criterion Three, Items "C" and "D."
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30-April 1, 2009, 1988; 2004-2009; undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  These materials came from the Office of the Associate Provost for Academic Affairs, Dr. Kandi Stinson. They are a collection of documents and reports which her office gathered as reference materials for the preparation and writing of the HLC Self-Study. The papers in this folder pertain to Criterion Four, Items "A" and "B."
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30-April 1, 2009, 2008-2009; undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  These materials came from the Office of the Associate Provost for Academic Affairs, Dr. Kandi Stinson. They are a collection of documents and reports which her office gathered as reference materials for the preparation and writing of the HLC Self-Study. the papers in this folder pertain to Criterion Four, Items "C" and "D."
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of March 30-April 1, 2009, 2008-2009; undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  These materials came from the Office of the Associate Provost for Academic Affairs, Dr. Kandi Stinson. They are a collection of documents and reports which her office gathered as reference materials for the preparation and writing of the HLC Self-Study. The papers in this folder pertain to Criterion Five, Items "A" through "D."
- Higher Learning Commission/ North Central Association Visit of April 4-6 2011 (Box 11, Folder 6)